hi welcome back to the
wheel of life at home retreat
where this horse race is almost finished
and we reached section 24 out of 25
sessions
and this this session is called my hair
on fire
and the picture you see here is of a guy
with his clothes and his hair are both
on fire
[Music]
and i think it's interesting that
pabonko and bucher quotes it so
frequently in his
long ramp
because i had the good fortune to work
on that text a lot when i was very young
my friend art angle a fellow student a
dear fellow student
and my teacher translated that book
rim so we tend to think of the
alarm rim the steps of the path teaching
started in tibet but it's not true
[Music]
almost 2 000 years ago it's kind of a
really beautiful alarm
and by the way this happened with
somebody in during my
uh if your clothes or your hair catch on
fire
you're not gonna do some other things
you're gonna immediately do whatever you
can to stop them
then we have a job like that
we want to put out the fire of rebirth
uh we have a very short time in the
district
while you are healthy well you can still
meditate while your mind is still clear
don't hit them
you don't have time to do a lot of other
things
this fire is burning you know
so you have to stop everything else and
try to
put out this fight
there's nothing more important you have
to do in your life
and uh generally in my life
i have followed this in my life
generally
and and the fact is that there are
if you want to put out that fire
you will not have time to do many other
things
so you you might have to give up many of
the things that other people do in their
life
and i've been doing that for
[Music]
so like for example i'm very bad
at buying birthday presents for my
family
and it's not that i don't love them we
love each other very much
but if i spend the time to go to the
store to pick a gift for every family
member we have a
[Music]
do my meditation practice every day
without breaking it to go to the store
to buy a breakfast
now they didn't go home
and then the the daily study and
practice of morality which i need to
support my meditation
the guardian says here waiting
[Music]
that says here it's just like your hair
is on fire
there's nothing else more important
right now
put out that fire then do it
become a buddha and then buy birthday
gifts
how are you going to put out this fight
uh if you remember these are the three
parts of the wood cutter
with
good focus like that unshaking flame
to hit in the right place
and then two strong arms of morality to
swing the axe
[Music]
then if you use those three down
you
you have controlled yourself completely
the state beyond all impurities
[Music]
friend number 2
uh you will you should try to reach that
and by the way also get rid of the sun
and the moon
okay now uh that last line
i thought we should go on a little side
trip which i like to do
of course i don't have negative emotions
anymore it's peaceful
i'm self-controlled of course
no more problems in my body no more
problems
my life pure life goes on forever
and i went to get you some commentaries
today
uh the one i enjoyed the most was by a
great mongolian
author
his name is
and here's his commentary to that last
one
so we're going deeper and that's what we
do and that's why this long room
teaching is
you don't have this normal body cocoa
made of these four elements
uh you have what we call a rainbow buddy
why is it called rainbow bike that
sounds good
from a distance a rainbow looks like it
has a shape and it looks like it has
colors
but then when you come up close to the
rainbow
this is a famous book called the
extraordinary praises or something
this praise of the one who is
extraordinarily
superior
no he's going to quote he's going to
quote a book
it's a famous eulogy eulogy means a poem
of praise found in the things
and it says
which is probably a mistake uh and
everything is
misspelled and miscarried here okay so i
had to replace a lot of words
okay but he says uh
type
m with his big
boy and then they say he got to nirvana
no i know that man what's that all about
you don't know this is supposed to
explain the sun and the moon
there's no more sun there's no more
lazar
means a hindu saint
hindu he's called
[Music]
with some miracle powers
who is a great great master
he says uh oh shanti davos sorry uh
they are criticizing this idea that
nirvana is some place
on the other side of the moon or
something like that
so he criticizes he says son and
when the book says you are free of the
sun and the moon it means
you are free of this dumb idea about
words what is nirvana
young
[Music]
it says or some people think when you
reach nirvana
you go into some white lights
it's like the color of snow no zombies
it looks like an umbrella covers you
and these are all weird ideas
so when he says when this book says you
go beyond the sun
it means you go beyond these dumb ideas
about oh
nirvana is like a big umbrella that's
colored white and
you stay in under the umbrella
[Music]
and you can say those are just stupid
old ideas from some
weird groups in india
and maybe it's not much different from
the white umbrellas
now just for fun uh which i enjoy doing
i thought you would like to go
[Music]
this is a book by pabong karambiche
himself
and this is a beautiful kind of genre of
book it's a type of literature
so even in this course we're going to be
doing a special master class
and i'll be accepting questions from you
and i'll be giving answers
and also in the uh expanded course
you'll be able to ask questions directly
online or in person
or by internet to senior
aci teachers
but in the ancient times somebody would
sit there you know
like carving the question
so here's a question that somebody
actually asked
so what about that last line of the
letter to a friend which
talks about you reach nirvana where you
don't have sun and moon
oh and here's pablo's own answer because
he didn't answer
and he didn't ask the questions
and by the way this is the great benefit
that we have five
million pages of scriptures
digitalized in the last 33 years
and i know many of you watching this
alarm room are helping
to organize fundraising for that digital
list
and i wanted to thank you and the reason
i can
go deeper
it's because of your fundraising
and it definitely helps poor people
around the world who we train
and it's beautiful now as some of those
ladies that i met
in the first year of this project
okay so here it says
some people uh
ancient weird schools
these are strange ideas that nirvana
is a physical place
but if you really want to go to the real
me
you need those three trainings
morality no type concentration
okay uh
yeah i have to say uh a lot of people
think though that
if you study this section that we've
covered with 25 classes
if you study it well
and you know people think it's like
you got very drunk
and you are like this okay
and you are just like in another space
you know
this is not nirvana
[Music]
look dude for you the person sitting
next to you
they could have reached nirvana last
night because of this great classes
and they're not going to change their
outer appearances
they don't have any more negative
emotions
and you cannot make them so
but that kind of going deeper is only
possible because we have a database that
we built for 33 years
[Music]
video
so i hope you will continue to help and
i thank you for your help so far
not learning about a phone club
especially
gold club friends not be learning about
a world club
okay
well what is it that people in this
medium
motivation
they just want to stop suffering forever
for themselves
well what should they be focusing on
uh those three extraordinary trainings
[Music]
now if i wasn't going to teach you
guys the highest
your whole body changes your whole mind
changes you're able to help people
on billions of planets at the same time
yeah nirvana just means me one person
here on this couch
i don't have anger i don't have jobs
which might by the way that means you
got out of the wheel of foreign
[Music]
and you are able to help countless
beings on countless planets at the same
time
so
the details of those three trainings
today
i am gonna teach you those higher goals
so i think we'll save two of those
trainings for later
training deep meditation
training
after we finish this book because
pabonko doesn't spend
much time on shamatha and vipassana in
this book
a little bit but not much
at the end of this book we're going to
go to the great book on the steps of
japan
[Music]
we will just do the part on shamathan
jungkook
okay so so i'm telling you and pabong is
telling you
we'll get to there later those two
trainings
tradition at this point we just focus on
morality because we're going to teach
you something
later
[Music]
uh how can i describe the practice
of living an ethical world
well think about this
planet earth the big dirt the huge huge
huge
all the countries are arrested
the dirt of this planet holds up
everything that's moving
and everything that's not moving
[Music]
these red mountains in the background
are very very famous six million people
a year come here
and the earth patiently quietly
holds up those mountains all day all
night
and the earth patiently holds them up
so whether things are moving like the
cars or whether things are not moving
like the red mountains the earth is very
patient he just holds the invite
is like the cars come together
somebody patient quiet
always there has to be under foundation
nintendo
being nice to other people is the
foundation of every good quality
therefore never
hurting any other person is extremely
important
we now have
if you keep an ethical way of life if
you are nice to other people
the benefits that come to you are
unbelievable
and if you don't keep to an ethical way
of life and you do hurt other people
you cannot imagine the kind of trouble
you are making for yourself
i'll tell you another important thing
that buddha said about
being nice to other people
if people in any city or country
are keeping their commitment to be nice
to other people
then buddha said then buddhism is there
foreign and if they're not keeping those
kind of commitment to be nice to other
people
then then i you cannot say buddhism
then it repeats
if there's one person in a city
keeping to a way of life where they
never hurt other people
then buddhism exists in that city
[Music]
people are practicing the highest
teaching there but they are not
moral
part of me will stay in this world
and that part of me will be your teacher
forever
that's keeping your vows
say i'm still here
uh final sentence
of this series
and then the 25th session will be a
review
so listen and let it be like a mantra
for you you know listen to the words
it's a blessing
other people's
[Music]
you are keeping this way of life
okay you don't have to be perfect but
those of you who are trying to keep your
six times
since you heard about this teaching
about seeds
you
as long as you're generally
imperfectly trying to be nice to other
people
uh in session 25 we're going to do a
review of the whole
25 sessions
toy